let's look at the solution to our
performance versus number of cores quiz
if chip power is a hundred watts and we
can operate one core if that's the only
one on the chip at five gigahertz how
many gigahertz do we get for two cores
and the answer is that each of the two
cores now gets 50 watts
that's half the power
the frequency in that case is going to
be the cubic root of that one half
or 0.8 times the original frequency so
we get 4 gigahertz here the frequency
with another doubling of the number of
cores is that each gets half the power
of these
so it's going to be 0.8 times this
which is going to be 3.2 or
we could do cubic root of one quarter of
the original five gigahertz and get the
same answer here
for execution time we need to account
for the change in frequency as well
as the change in parallelism so this is
what we get we get 100 seconds
when we run all of these pieces
at just one core at five gigahertz if we
ignore the frequency
and have a two chord chip then what we
get is that
for twenty percent of the time we get a
parallelism of only one with two cores
for the remaining eighty percent of the
execution time
we now have a speed up
of two
so that time is cut in half so we get
0.6 times the original time
if we ignore the frequency so it would
be 60 seconds without the change in
frequency unfortunately there is a
change in frequency
60 seconds at 5 gigahertz
would translate so we get 60 seconds
times 5 billion cycles per second is 75
seconds at 4 billion cycles per second
so the answer here is 75 seconds we
would get 60 if we operated at 5
gigahertz
but because we operated 4
we need 75 and then for a 4 core
execution
we get that
out of the 100 seconds for 20 seconds we
can't improve by running on more cores
for 30 seconds we get a speed up of 2
because we can use 2 cores for 40
seconds the speed up is 3 because we can
use 3 of the 4 cores
and finally
for 10 seconds we get a speed up of 4.
keep in mind that this is without the
change in frequency so what we get
is 50.8 seconds
and now we have to account
for the change in frequency from 5
gigahertz to 3.2 gigahertz
so once we get the 50.8 seconds that's
without the change in frequency and we
get from 5 to 3.2
so when we compute the speed up relative
to this because of a lower frequency
which is actually a slowdown and we
multiply that with this we get 79.4
which is actually slower
than a two core execution so as you can
see although the four core execution
gets some more parallelism exploited
it's not enough to make up for the lost
in performance due to frequency change